L.S.M. Curtin papers, 1930-1953
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
L.S.M. Curtin papers, 1930-1953
MS 395
Curtin, L.S.M.
Papers (ca. 1930-1953) The papers of L.S.M Curtin document her professional and personal activities as an ethnobotanist in the southwest region. The collection contains material relating to the ethnobotanical fieldwork she pursued in Arizona, New Mexico, and Mexico as well as the subsequent publication of her book By Prophet of the Earth (1949). The collection also includes materials pertaining to her various travels and personal and professional relationships with friends, colleagues, patrons, and publishers.
.75 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
L. S. M. Curtin was an avid naturalist, ethnobotanist, and a published author. Her ethnobotanical research was primarily concerned with the use of herbs and plants being used as diet staples and medicine among southwestern ethnic and indigenous groups. She is the author of four published monographs and various journal articles. Her extensive ethnobotanical fieldwork led to the publication of her two most noted works, Healing Herbs of the Upper Rio Grande (1947) and By Prophet of the Earth (1949), which highlights her fieldwork on the Salt River Indian Reservation and the Pueblo Grande Laboratory.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1940-1953
Subseries 1.1 Business, 1940-1953
Subseries 1.2 Personal, 1942-1953
Series II: Fieldwork, ca. 1930s-1940s
Series III: Manuscripts, 1949
Series IV: Photographs/Negatives, 1940-1942
Series V: Printed Material, ca.1930s-1940s
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1930-1953 (bulk 1940-1953), of ethnobotanist, naturalist, and author L.S.M. Curtin. Includes business and personal correspondence, fieldwork, photographs and negatives, maps, printed material, and a manuscript of her published monograph By Prophet of the Earth (1949). The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence pertaining to her professional activities as a published author and her ethnobotanical fieldwork in Arizona, New Mexico, and Michoacan, Mexico.
Access Terms
Brown, Howell C.-Correspondence
Curtin, L. S. M. (Leonora Scott Muse)
Pima Indians
Tarasco Indians
Indians of North American--Medicine
Indians of North American--Food
Indians of North America--Ethnobotany
Ethnographic Photographs
Correspondence
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1940-1953
  - Series 1.1 Business, 1940-1953
    - De la Borbolla, Daniel R. 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Brown, Howell C. 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Harrington, J.P. 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hodge, F.W. 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Wessels, Myrtilla A. 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General 1940-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Series 1.2 Personal, 1942-1953
    - Brown, Howell C. 1942-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Brown, Sibley 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Coze Paul 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - General n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Fieldwork, 1930s-1940s
  - Pueblo Grande Laboratory ca.1940s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Salt River Indian Reservation ca. 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tarascan ca. 1940s (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III: Manuscript, 1949
  - By Prophet of the Earth 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
- Series IV: Photographs/Negatives, 1940-1942
  - Photographs-Salt River Indian Reservation 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Negatives-Salt River Indian Reservation 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Negatives- L.S.M. Curtin Home, Santa Fe, N.M n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series V: Printed Materials, ca. 1930s-1940s
  - Printed Materials ca. 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 9)